Guide to the John Bartlet Brebner Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
John Bartlet Brebner Papers
1937-1957.
Brebner, John Bartlet, 1895-1957.
11 linear ft (26 boxes).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
4079650
History
Gouverneur Morris Professor of History at Columbia University (Ph.D. 1927).
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, notes, and printed materials. This collection consists of his correspondence (1937-1957) in four boxes; manuscripts, notes, and printed copies of speeches and periodical articles and the manuscripts of "North Atlantic Triangle" and "Making of Modern Canada". Included also are the notes for a number of courses given by him at Columbia University as well as three boxes of student seminar papers. Most of the materials in the collection relate to some phase of Canadian life and history.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into two series:
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Manuscripts and Documents
Subjects
Canada--Civilization.; Canada--History.; Addresses.; Articles.; Diplomas.; Examinations.; Maps.; Reports.; Scripts.; Speeches.; Syllabi.; Historians.
Acquisition
1958 M-1958 Brebner, Elliot J. Gift
Gift of Elliot J. Brebner, 1958.
Access Restrictions
Box 1 of this collection is onsite. The remainder of this collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least two business days in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Cataloged Correspondence
    - Lester Bowles Pearson Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1937-1957 (arranged by year) (Box 1-4)
- Series II: Documents
  - Memoranda on Upper College, Columbia College (Box 5)
  - Memoranda on Bard College (Box 5)
  - H. A. Innis: cuttings (obituaries, etc) and correspondence about him (Box 5)
  - Business concerning North Atlantic Triangle--mostly with Yale University Press (Box 5)
  - Address, "Man's Right to Knowledge," at Ottawa, 1954--copy and offprints (Box 5)
  - Address, "Keystone in the Arch, Centenary, University College, Toronto, 1956 (Box 5)
  - Bicentennial Oration, "The Common Ground in Humility"--correspondence and clippings (Box 5)
  - Stockholm address, "Man's Right to Knowledge," 1954 (Box 5)
  - Essay on Elie Halevy--drafts and copy (Box 5)
  - Encyclopedia Americana, article on Canada since 1867 (Box 6)
  - Chapter in U.N Volume on Canada: Drafts and correspondence (Box 6)
  - "Laissez-faire and State Intervention," draft and correspondence (Box 6)
  - Draft AHA comment on L. H. Gipson's paper on "The American Revolution as an Aftermath of the Great War for Empire," 1948 (Box 6)
  - General Staff Course, Washington, notes, address, and correspondence, 1948 (Box 6)
  - Informal talk to English-Speaking Union, "Democratic Foundations of Government," 1948 (Box 6)
  - CBC Talk, "The Canadian Personality," 1948--copy and correspondence (Box 6)
  - Economic History Association, 1947 (Box 6)
  - Address at Winnipeg, "History and Current Social Trends," 1946 (Box 6)
  - North Atlantic Triangle--correspondence and reviews, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Scholarship for Canada (Box 7)
  - Convocation Address, McMaster University--"General Education and Research," 1945 (Box 7)
  - Canadian Universities Materials (Box 7)
  - Reports, Canadian Universities, 1944 (Box 7)
  - Making of Modern Britain correspondence (Box 7)
  - Correspondence on G.L. Beer's MSS (Box 7)
  - Canadian Historical Association Presidential Address--"Canadianism"--Notes, Copy, and Correspondence, 1940 (Box 7)
  - Toronto Conference, United States and World Organization (Box 8)
  - "The British Social Welfare State"--OWI talk, 1943 (Box 8)
  - ERPI film on Early North American discovery: script and correspondence, 1942 (Box 8)
  - "Tadoussac, Kingdom of the Saguenay," 1942 (Box 8)
  - "The United States, Canada's Problem," Notes and copy, PTA, 1940 (Box 8)
  - "Canadian-American Relations in a Changing World"--address to U.M.C.A. at Couchiching, 1940 (Box 8)
    (contains draft, copy, and correspondence)
  - "The Ogdensburg Agreement between Canada and the United States"--Inter-American Quarterly, 1940 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence concerining Hanson's Mingling of the Canadian and American Peoples, completed by Brebner (Box 8)
  - Correspondence concerning map for Neutral Yankees. (Box 9)
  - "Canada, the Anglo-Japanese Alliance and the Washington Conference PSQ 1935 (Box 9)
    (contains notes,draft, offprint, and correspondence)
  - CHR--Dr. Andrew Brown MSS: draft, copy, and correspondence (Box 9)
  - DAB--Samuel Vetch (1668-1732), first military and second colonial governor of Nova Scotia (Box 9)
  - Louis Delisle de la Croyere MSS--correspondence (Box 9)
  - Kingston National Defence College, 1948 1950 1953 (Box 9)
  - Canadian Social Science Research Councils correspondence (Box 9)
  - Correspondence concerning Carnegie series on relations of Canada and the United States, 1968 (Box 10)
  - Reviews, etc., for Explorers (Box 11)
  - Materials for Neutral Yankees (Box 11)
  - Correspondence and Materials for New England's Outpost. (Box 11)
  - Mingling of Canadian and American Peoples Manuscript (Box 11)
  - Criticisms of North Atlantic Triangle (Box 12)
  - North Atlantic Triangle Manuscript (Box 12)
  - Outlines of plan for Canadian-American series, 1933 (2 brochures)_ (Box 12)
  - Notes for Canada in North American History, the Columbia course (Box 13)
  - Draft, Making of Modern Canada (Box 14)
  - Canadian-American maps. (Box 15)
  - British historical materials before 1850--offprints, clippings, notes, etc. (Box 15)
  - "Under George III," Conference on British Studies, 1955 (Box 15)
  - British Constitutional History (Box 15)
  - Cambridge lectures on Anglo-American relations (Box 15)
  - Fulbright seminar on migration, 1951 (Box 15)
  - Britain since 1776 the Columbia course and basis of proposed book on industrial Britain (Box 16, 17, 18, 35)
  - 3 x 5 cards--notes on Nova Scotia (Neutral Yankees ) (Box 19)
  - Industrial Britain, MS, four chapters (Box 19)
  - Paul Mascarene (Box 20)
  - "Collectivist Britain" ms. notes (Box 20)
  - "Some aspects of Great Britain between wars" ms. notes (Box 20)
  - Canada-2 course outlines (Box 20)
  - Rockefeller grant: correspondence Etc. (Box 20)
  - Recommendations for scholarship & fellowship awards: correspondence (Box 20)
  - Seminar information (Box 20)
  - Examination questions in history (Box 20)
  - Candidacies 1938-1946 (Box 21)
  - Student Papers (Box 22-24)
  - Diplomas of John Bartlet Brebner (Box 22-24)
  - Periodicals with articles by John Bartlet Brebner (Box 25-26)